重役[じゅうやく, おもやく]:company director/top management/high executive, タンデム:tandem/(riding with a) passenger on a motorcycle, ミラー:mirror, エンジン:engine, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 機[はた]:loom
（重役１）タンデムミラー
エンジン２号機の―
Damage resulting from the meltdown of the #2
tandem mirror engine has reached 800 billion.
メルトダウン:meltdown, 損害[そんがい]:damage/injury/loss
メルトダウンによる
損害は―
億[おく]:10^8/100,000,000/hundred million, 上る[あがる]:to rise|to enter (esp. from outdoors)|to enter (a school)||, 上る[のぼる]:to ascend|to ascend (as a natural process, e.g. the sun)|to go to (the capital)||
８,０００億に
上っています
重役[じゅうやく, おもやく]:company director/top management/high executive, 我が社[わがしゃ]:our company/my company, イメージ:(one's) image, 悪化[あっか]:(suffer) deterioration/growing worse/aggravation, 深刻[しんこく]:serious/severe/grave
（重役２）我が社の
イメージ悪化も深刻です
There has also been a serious worsening
of the company's public image.
フォン:phon (unit of loudness), ブラウン:brown, 号[ごう]:number|sobriquet|suffix attached to names of ships, trains, airplanes, etc., 建造[けんぞう]:building/construction
フォン･ブラウン号の
建造は―
Technora is the key figure in the construction
of the Von Braun, after all.
社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc., 中心[ちゅうしん]:center/centre|-centered, 中心[なかご]:core|tang (of a sword, etc.)|middle of a nest of boxes
テクノーラ社が中心に
なっていますからね
重役[じゅうやく, おもやく]:company director/top management/high executive, 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, 起こる[おこる]:to occur/to happen
（重役３）次に
大きな事故が起これば―
If there is another serious accident, we'll be
looking not only at a setback for the project,
計画[けいかく]:plan/project/schedule, 頓挫[とんざ]:setback/deadlock/being at a standstill or impasse, もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally
計画の頓挫は もちろん―
莫大[ばくだい]:enormous/vast|malva nut (Sterculia lychnophora), 金銭[きんせん]:money/cash, 補償[ほしょう]:compensation/reparation, 世間[せけん]:world/society, 悪評[あくひょう]:bad reputation/infamy/ill repute, 負う[おう]:to bear|to take responsibility for|to be injured|, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
莫大な金銭補償と
世間の悪評を負うことになります
...but also massive financial settlement
payments and a public scandal.
Which is one of the reasons why
we must put some distance...
木星[もくせい]:Jupiter (planet), 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, 計画[けいかく]:plan/project/schedule, 我が社[わがしゃ]:our company/my company
そのためにも
木星開発計画と我が社は―
...between our company and the
Jupiter development project.
距離[きょり]:distance/range, 置く[おく]:to put|to leave (behind)|to establish (an organization, a facility, a position, etc.)||, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
距離を置く必要がある
We need a warning bell,
as well.
重役[じゅうやく, おもやく]:company director/top management/high executive, 鈴[すず, りん]:bell (often globular), 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
（重役２）鈴も必要ですし
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
（会長）それで この会社ですか
And that is why you've
created this company.
Galileo Development. We're working through
three levels of intermediary companies,
重役[じゅうやく, おもやく]:company director/top management/high executive, ガリレオ:Galileo, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation
（重役４）ガリレオ開発―
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 経由[けいゆ, けいゆう]:through/by way of|to go via, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
３つの会社を
経由していますので―
法的[ほうてき]:legal, 完全[かんぜん]:perfection/completeness, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
法的には 完全に別会社です
...so legally speaking, it is a completely
independent entity.
I'm sending Dolf Azaria, the current Second
Division Director that I mentioned the other day,
新[しん]:new|Gregorian calendar|Xin (dynasty of China), 新[さら, あら]:new|new|obvious, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 代表取締役[だいひょうとりしまりやく]:representative director/managing director/president
（専務）
新会社には代表取締役として―
先日[せんじつ]:the other day/a few days ago, お話し[おはなし]:story/tale, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 出向[しゅっこう]:secondment/temporary transfer|proceeding
先日 お話しした 第２事業部部長
ドルフ･アザリアを出向させます
...to act as representative director
of the new company.
うーん:hmm/well, 空席[くうせき]:empty seat/unoccupied seat|vacancy, ポスト:post/position
うーん 空席となったポストは？
What about the post
he'll be vacating?
本日[ほんじつ]:today, 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department
（ノーマン）
本日より 第２事業部を―
I'm Norman Schwimmer, and I've been put in
charge of Second Division starting today.
任す[まかす]:to entrust/to leave to a person, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
任されることになった
ノーマン･シュワイマーだ
On the insistence of Chairman Joshua,
I will be serving concurrently...
会長[かいちょう]:president (of a society)/chairman, 是非[ぜひ]:certainly/without fail|right and wrong, 声がかり[こえがかり]:recommendation of an influential person
ヨシュア会長から
是非にとのお声がかりで―
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 兼務[けんむ]:holding two posts concurrently, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
第３事業部部長と
兼務することになった
...as director of both Second
and Third Divisions.
アハハ:a-ha-ha (laughing loudly), 兼務[けんむ]:holding two posts concurrently, とはいえ:though/although/be that as it may
アハハ
兼務とはいえ 今日から私が―
Now, while this may be an additional post
for me, it doesn't change the fact...
第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, トップ:top, 変わり[かわり]:change|unusual state or event|difference
第２事業部の
トップであることに変わりはない
...that I am the top dog in
Second Division starting today.
I'm going to be running things
my own way from now on.
やり方[やりかた]:manner of doing/way/method, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
これからは
私のやり方でやらせてもらう
いいな
Is that clear?
I suggest that you forget everything about
how the old director ran the division.
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, やり方[やりかた]:manner of doing/way/method, 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
前の事業部長のやり方は
全て忘れるように
♪～
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
時空[じくう]:space-time, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 夢を見る[ゆめをみる]:to dream/to have a dream
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
静寂[せいじゃく, しじま]:silence/stillness/quietness, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
鳥[とり]:bird|bird meat (esp. chicken meat)/fowl, 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
儚い[はかない]:fleeting/transient|empty (dream, etc.), 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
幾[いく]:some|many|how many?, 幾[ほとほと]:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 千[せん, ち]:1,000/thousand, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
♪幾千の朝に
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
♪光が向かう場所へ
羽ばたく[はばたく]:to flap (wings)|to spread one's wings/to go out into the world
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
フロンティア:frontier
♪フロンティアへ
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 解散[かいさん]:breakup/dissolution
（タナベ）
えっ デブリ課が解散？
Debris Section's
gonna be disbanded?!
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill
（ラビィ）えっ
（課長）さっき―
I was just told in person
by Director Norman.
Phase 18
Debris Section's Last Day
新[しん]:new|Gregorian calendar|Xin (dynasty of China), 新[さら, あら]:new|new|obvious, 事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 直接[ちょくせつ]:direct/immediate/personal
ノーマン新事業部長から
直接 言われた
He said we'll be disbanded
at the end of the week.
今週末[こんしゅうまつ]:this weekend, 解散[かいさん]:breakup/dissolution
今週末で解散だって
企業[きぎょう]:enterprise/undertaking/corporation, 体裁[ていさい, たいさい]:(outward) appearance|(proper) format (e.g. of an essay)|appearances|, 収益[しゅうえき]:earnings/proceeds/returns, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect)
企業としての体裁より
収益が大事とかで
Something about earnings being more
important to a company than its image.
（ラビィ）そんな
He can't! What's gonna
happen to us?
我々[われわれ]:we, 異動[いどう]:change (personnel)/transfer/reshuffle
（ラビィ）
じゃ 我々はどうなるんです？
異動ですか？ それとも…
Will we be transferred? Or...
Fired.
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
（エーデル）クビ
（タナベ）まさか
They wouldn't!
リストラ:(corporate) restructuring/downsizing
（課長）いや そうかも
リストラとか言ってたし
No, she might be right.
He mentioned something about downsizing.
（ラビィ）うっそー
（課長）本当
You're kidding!
It's true!
じじい:old man|old geezer
（フィー）あのじじい
That old bastard still has it in for us
over what happened with that test module.
実験[じっけん]:experiment, モジュール:module, 件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item, 根に持つ[ねにもつ]:to hold a grudge/to hold something against somebody, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
実験モジュールの件
まだ根に持ってやがるな
反対[はんたい]:opposition/resistance|reverse
（ラビィ）だから
あのとき 私は反対したんだ
That's why I was against getting involved!
Look what you've done!
どうしてくれるんだよ！
家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family, 養う[やしなう]:to support|to bring up|to adopt (a child)||, いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
家族だって
養わなくちゃいけないのに
I still have a family
to provide for!
Um... I thought you and
your wife had split up.
奥さん[おくさん]:wife/your wife/his wife, 別れる[わかれる]:to part (usu. of people)|to separate (of a couple)|to lose (e.g. one's mother)
（タナベ）あの…
奥さんとは別れたんじゃ？
Maybe, but I had seven
children with her!
女房[にょうぼう, にょうぼ]:wife (esp. one's own wife)|court lady|woman (esp. as a love interest), 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 子供[こども]:child/children
でも 女房との間には
７人の子供がいるの！
養育費[よういくひ]:child-rearing expenses/child-support payments (following divorce), 倍[ばい]:twice/double|times
つまり 養育費も７倍
That means child support
times seven!
そりゃあ:very/extremely|that is, ぶっちぎり:establishing a large lead over one's competitors/breaking away (from the field), 赤字[あかじ]:deficit|red text|corrections (by a teacher or proofreader) written in red
そりゃあさ
うちはぶっちぎりで赤字だし―
But we're always running deep in the red, and
we don't have any connections at the top!
上にもコネないけどさ
Quit your damn crying!
泣く[なく]:to cry/to weep/to sob, うっとうしい:gloomy (e.g. mood)/depressing|irritating, 限る[かぎる]:to restrict/to limit|to be restricted to
（フィー）泣くな！ うっとうしい
まだ クビとは限らないだろ
Nobody said we're
gonna be fired!
接待[せったい]:reception/welcome|wining and dining
（ラビィ）そうだ 接待だ
She's right!
Let's wine and dine them!
接待[せったい]:reception/welcome|wining and dining, 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
みんなで接待して
なんとかして許してもらうんだ
We'll all entertain them to smooth things over
and try to get him to forgive us!
なっ？
Right?
派遣[はけん]:dispatch/despatch|temporary employee (esp. from an agency)
私は派遣ですから
I'm only a
temp worker.
あ…
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 解散[かいさん]:breakup/dissolution
（タナベ）先輩 大変です
デブリ課が解散しちゃうって
Senpai! This is terrible!
They say Debris Section
is gonna be disbanded!
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
（ハチマキ）ああ 聞こえてたよ
Yeah, I heard you
in there.
No matter how precious their profits are to
them, don't you think this is going too far?
いくら:how much?/how many?|even, 収益[しゅうえき]:earnings/proceeds/returns, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), あんまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence)
いくら収益が大事だからって
あんまりだと思いません？
（ハチマキ）ああ そうだな
Yeah, I guess.
If we don't come up with a way to keep
them from disbanding us, we're gonna...
解散[かいさん]:breakup/dissolution, 私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us
（タナベ）解散させないように
私たちも何かしないと
解散[かいさん]:breakup/dissolution, 私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us
（タナベ）解散させないように
私たちも何かしないと
（ハチマキ）そうだな
Yeah, I guess...
とりあえず:first of all/at once|for now, 飯[めし]:cooked rice|meal|one's livelihood, 飯[まんま, まま]:cooked rice, 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
（ハチマキ）
とりあえず 飯食いに行くわ
Let's get something to eat. I'm starving.
腹[はら]:abdomen|womb|one's mind||, 減る[へる]:to decrease (in size or number)/to diminish/to abate
腹 減った
は？
Huh?
Aren't you supposed
to be working today?
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
（ハキム）
今日は 仕事じゃなかったのか？
営業[えいぎょう]:business/trade/sales, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 資料[しりょう]:materials/data/document, 整理[せいり]:sorting|liquidation|retrenchment
営業軌道の資料を整理をするとか
Sorting management orbit
paperwork or some such?
サボり:skipping out/cutting class/truancy
（クレア）サボり
（ハキム）え？
I'm playing hooky.
It's all right.
（クレア）いいの
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 外す[はずす]:to unfasten|to remove|to leave|
どうせ仕事は 全部 外されちゃって
やることないから
Anyway, I've been taken off all my duties,
so I don't have anything to do.
（ハキム）どうして？
Why's that?
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 失敗[しっぱい]:failure/mistake/blunder, 続く[つづく]:to continue|to continue (without a break)|to occur again and again||
最近 失敗続きだったし―
I've had one failure
after another lately.
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 派[は]:clique/faction/school, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
前の事業部長派って
思われてるみたい
Plus, I guess they think I'm a member
of the old division director's clique.
派閥[はばつ]:clique/faction, 争い[あらそい]:dispute/strife/quarrel
（ハキム）派閥争いか
Political infighting, huh?
ばかばかしい:absurd/ridiculous/silly
なんか ばかばかしくなっちゃった
It all seems so stupid
to me now.
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 降りる[おりる]:to descend (e.g. a mountain)|to alight (e.g. from bus)|to step down||, 結婚[けっこん]:marriage
地球に降りて結婚でもしよっかな
Maybe I'll go down to Earth and
get married or something.
嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant, 黙る[だまる]:to be silent, 冗談[じょうだん, ぎだん]:jest/joke/funny story
嫌だ 黙らないでよ 冗談…
Come on, don't go silent on me. I was joking.
- Claire.
（ハキム）クレア
（クレア）え？
国[くに]:country|region|national government||
（ハキム）
マナンガって国を知ってるかい？
Do you know a country
named Mananga?
中東[ちゅうとう]:Middle East, 産油国[さんゆこく]:oil-producing countries (nations)
中東の産油国ね
An oil-producing country
in the Middle East, right?
石油[せきゆ]:oil/petroleum/kerosene, 内乱[ないらん]:civil war/insurrection/rebellion, 続く[つづく]:to continue|to continue (without a break)|to occur again and again||
石油が使われなくなってからは
内乱続きって聞いたけど
I'd heard that there's been constant civil wars
there ever since oil stopped being used.
ふるさと:home town/birthplace|ruins
（ハキム）僕のふるさとだ
（クレア）え？
It's my homeland.
貧困[ひんこん]:poor/needy|lacking, 内乱[ないらん]:civil war/insurrection/rebellion, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||, 政府[せいふ]:government/administration, 分裂[ぶんれつ]:split/division/break up, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation
（ハキム）
貧困が内乱を呼び 政府は分裂状態
Poverty triggered the civil wars, and
the government is in a state of chaos.
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 手を借りる[てをかりる]:to accept help/to get help/to ask for help, 選挙[せんきょ]:election, 満足[まんぞく]:satisfaction/contentment|sufficient
連合の手を借りないと
選挙も満足にできない
We can't even hold fair elections
without going to INTO for help.
祖国[そこく]:motherland/fatherland/native country
それが僕の祖国なんだ
That's what my homeland
is like.
You're taking personal command
out here today, ma'am?
自ら[おのずから]:naturally/as a matter of course, 自ら[みずから]:oneself|for one's self/personally, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 陣頭[じんとう]:head of an army, 指揮[しき]:command/direction
（社員）今日は あねさん自ら
外で陣頭指揮ですか？
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
（フィー）
ああ これで最後らしいから
Yeah, 'cause it looks like this
is gonna be the last time.
船乗り[ふなのり]:getting on board|sailor/seaman, 流儀[りゅうぎ]:style/fashion|school (e.g. of poetry)
まっ 船乗りの流儀ってやつでね
It's sort of a tradition
among sailors.
ユーリ そっちはどう？
Yuri, how's it look
on your end?
Fine. All green.
問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
（ユーリ）ああ 問題ない
（フィー）何？
What?
Are you okay with this
being the last?
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments
（ユーリ）いいのか？ 最後で
There's not much we can do.
It's the boss' decision.
しかたない:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use, 決定[けってい]:decision/determination
（フィー）
しかたないでしょ 上の決定だもの
それに―
Besides, I can keep collecting debris
even if I'm not at Technora.
デブリ:debris, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather
デブリは
テクノーラにいなくても拾えるさ
You're going to
change companies?
移る[うつる]:to move (house)|to change the target of interest or concern|to elapse (passage of time)||, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
移るのか？ 会社
（フィー）さあ
I don't know... It wouldn't be the
first time I've switched companies,
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ...
（フィー）会社を変わるのは
初めてのことじゃないし―
...and there's also
what they did to Dolf.
ドルフのこともあるしね
Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey! I'm Lavie!
（ラビィ）はいはい はいはい
ラビィちゃんだよ
That was terrific! I haven't laughed
this hard in a long time!
傑作[けっさく]:masterpiece/best work|amusing blunder
（ノーマン）
いやー 傑作だ ハハハッ…
笑う[わらう]:to laugh|to smile|to sneer|, 久しぶり[ひさしぶり]:a long time (since the last time)/it's been a while (since I last saw, mailed, etc., you)
こんなに笑ったのは久しぶりだよ
総務課[そうむか]:general affairs section, 席[せき]:seat|location (of a gathering, etc.)|position, 席[むしろ, えん]:woven mat (esp. one made of straw)|seat, 用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision
いいだろう 君には
総務課の席を用意してやろう
All right, I'll find you a position in
General Affairs, how's that sound?
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
（ラビィ）
ははっ ありがとうございます
Thank you so much!
たまに:occasionally/once in a while, くだる:to descend/to go down|to be handed down (of an order, judgment, etc.)
（ノーマン）たまには こういう
くだらないのもいいもんだ
It does a man good to enjoy nonsense
like this every once in a while.
An astute observation, Director Norman!
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 部長[ぶちょう]:head (chief, director) of a section or department|head of a (school) club/head of a (school) team
さすがはノーマン部長
The last director wasn't able to
enjoy this kind of entertainment.
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager
前の事業部長は―
楽しむ[たのしむ]:to enjoy (oneself), 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||
こういう楽しみ方の
できない方でしたから
Dolf has no idea how to use his human resources, keeping a man like you down in Half Section like that.
人材[じんざい]:capable person/talented person|human resources, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 置く[おく]:to put|to leave (behind)|to establish (an organization, a facility, a position, etc.)||, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
君のような人材を
半課に置いておくなんて―
使い方[つかいかた]:way to use something/treatment/management (of help)
ドルフは人の使い方を知らんな
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, 連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 接待[せったい]:reception/welcome|wining and dining, よろしく:well/properly|best regards, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
今度の連合の接待も
よろしく頼むよ
I want you to handle the entertainment
the next time INTO visits.
うまい:skillful/skilful|delicious, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 約束[やくそく]:promise|convention|destiny
うまくいったら係長を約束しよう
If it works out,
there's a manager position in it for you.
Really? Not assistant manager?
補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance, 取れる[とれる]:to come off|(of pain, a fever, etc.) to disappear|to be caught||
えっ？ 補佐が取れるんですか？
I look forward to seeing you
crack us all up.
爆笑[ばくしょう]:roar of laughter (from several people)|laughing hard (single person), 芸[げい]:art/craft/accomplishment, 期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope
爆笑ものの芸 期待してるよ
Thank you so much, sir! Thank you!
ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
ありがとうございます
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
頑張ります
I'll give it
all I've got!
（タナベ）何やってんですか！
What the heck are
you doing?!
あっ…
This is no time to be reading
an EVA textbook!
今更[いまさら]:now (after such a long time)/at this late hour (i.e. it is too late for something)|afresh, 教本[きょうほん]:textbook, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess, 場合[ばあい]:case/situation
（タナベ）今更 ＥＶＡ教本なんて
読んでる場合じゃないでしょう？
Our team is about
to be split up!
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, バラバラ:scattered/disperse/loose
私たち
バラバラになっちゃうんですよ
You always said that space needed the Debris Section!
デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
デブリ屋は
宇宙に必要だって言った…
返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
（ハチマキ）おい 返せよ！
- Hey, give that back!
はい
Fine.
読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess, 結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||, 勉強になる[べんきょうになる]:to gain knowledge/to be illuminated|enlightening
３年ぶりに読んだけど
結構 勉強になるな これ
I haven't read this thing in three years.
It's got some useful info in it.
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 解散[かいさん]:breakup/dissolution
（タナベ）
デブリ課が解散したら―
If Debris Section gets disbanded, making EVAs
is gonna be the least of our worries, you know?
どころ:particle used to indicate that what precedes it is an extreme example and strongly negates it
ＥＶＡどころじゃ
ないじゃないですか
This isn't the only place
we can do EVA work.
（ハチマキ）ＥＶＡは
ここじゃなくてもできるだろ？
What about
debris retrieval?
デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
デブリの回収は？
Yeah, that's nice...
ああ そうだな
C'mon, Senpai...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
ねえ 先輩
もう いいです
Fine! Suit yourself!
I'll save Debris Section
all by myself if I have to!
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise)
私は１人でも
デブリ課を守りますから！
（ハチマキ）あっ…
No, honest! It's the truth!
（ラビィ）本当だ 本当なんだって
Daddy's gonna be made
into a manager!
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, 今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, 係長[かかりちょう]:chief clerk
お父さん 今度 係長になるんだぞ
子供[こども]:child/children
（子供１）ちゃー
（子供２）すごーい
Are you gonna
get paid more?
子供[こども]:child/children, 給料[きゅうりょう]:salary/wages, 上がる[あがる]:to rise|to enter (esp. from outdoors)|to enter (a school)||
（子供３）お給料も上がるの？
You bet, you bet!
上がる[あがる]:to rise|to enter (esp. from outdoors)|to enter (a school)||
上がる 上がる
Honest? Then buy me
a game!
ほんと:truth/reality|proper, ゲーム:game, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
ほんとに！ じゃ ゲーム買って
子供[こども]:child/children, サッカー:soccer, ボール:ball
（子供４）サッカーボール
A wanna
soccer ball!
子供[こども]:child/children, ちゃっちい:cheap/rubbishy/shoddy, 望遠鏡[ぼうえんきょう]:telescope
（子供１）ちゃー ちゃっちゃー
（子供５）私 望遠鏡
I want a telescope!
望遠鏡[ぼうえんきょう]:telescope, 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive, ゲーム:game, 遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys
望遠鏡は高いよ
ゲームなら みんなで遊べるのに
Telescopes are expensive!
If Dad buys a game, we all can play with it!
No, that's okay! It's to celebrate
Daddy moving up in the world.
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, 出世[しゅっせ]:success in life/getting ahead/successful career, お祝い[おいわい]:congratulation/congratulations/celebration
いいよ いいよ
お父さんが出世するお祝いだ
買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir
みんな買ってやるよ
I'll buy everything
you want!
子供[こども]:child/children, お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, 出世[しゅっせ]:success in life/getting ahead/successful career
（子供２）
ねえ お父さん 出世したら―
If you've got a bigger job, Daddy, that means
you're gonna pick up bigger de-breeze, right?
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather
もっといっぱい
デボを拾うんだよね？
子供[こども]:child/children, デブリ:debris
（子供３）バーカ デブリだよ
Dummy, it's pronounced "de-bree"!
総務課[そうむか]:general affairs section, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|
総務課の係長だからな
I'll be manager of General Affairs Section,
so I won't have to pick up debris anymore.
デブリ:debris, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather
もう デブリを
拾わなくてもいいんだ
（子供たち）え？
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise)
じゃあ 誰が宇宙を守るの？
Then who's gonna
keep space safe?
え？
They're blowing things
out of proportion.
大げさ[おおげさ]:grandiose/exaggerated
（ギガルト）
大げさにしよって
I'm not sick enough to be
put into the hospital yet.
入院[にゅういん]:hospitalization/hospitalisation, 通常[つうじょう]:common/general/normal, 勤務[きんむ]:service/duty/work
（ギガルト）
まだ入院するほどじゃあない
通常勤務なら…
I can still
handle everyday...
Absolutely not.
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 体調[たいちょう]:physical condition, 万全[ばんぜん]:perfection/flawlessness
駄目です
体調が万全でない者は―
Someone who isn't at 100% might put
the team as a whole in danger.
チーム:team, 全体[ぜんたい]:whole/entirety/whatever (is the matter), 危機[きき]:crisis/danger/risk, 陥れる[おとしいれる]:to trick someone into (committing a crime, etc.)|to assault (a castle, etc.)|to drop something and have it fall into something, 可能性[かのうせい]:potentiality/likelihood/possibility
チーム全体を
危機に陥れる可能性があります
教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
フッ フフフッ
俺が教えたんだったな
I taught you that,
didn't I?
コンディション:condition, 保つ[たもつ, もつ]:to keep/to preserve/to hold, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
コンディションを保つのも
仕事のうちだって
Maintaining your physical
condition is part of the job.
生意気[なまいき]:impertinent/saucy/cheeky
（ハキム）すいません 生意気を
I'm sorry if I spoke
out of turn, sir.
教え子[おしえご]:student/disciple, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
いや 俺は いい教え子を持ったな
Forget it.
I was lucky to have
such a good pupil.
先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy
（ハキム）先生
Sensei...
何だ？
Yeah?
I'm... quitting the Orbital Security Agency.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 保安庁[ほあんちょう]:National Security Board (1952-1954)
私は 軌道保安庁を…
I see... You're serious about this?
本気[ほんき]:seriousness/earnestness/truth
そうか 本気なんだな
（ハキム）はい
Yes, sir.
（タナベ）だから―
Like I said, my rank in the company
doesn't have anything to do with it!
平[ひら, ヒラ]:something broad and flat|common|low-ranking employee, 部長[ぶちょう]:head (chief, director) of a section or department|head of a (school) club/head of a (school) team, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
平も部長も関係ないって
言ってるじゃないですか
苦情[くじょう]:complaint/troubles/objection, 総務課[そうむか]:general affairs section, 人事[じんじ]:personnel affairs/human affairs/human resources, 人事[ひとごと, たにんごと]:other people's affairs/somebody else's problem, なさる:to do
（ゲイハート）
苦情なら 総務課人事に行きなさい
If you have a complaint, take it to General Affairs or Personnel!
苦情[くじょう]:complaint/troubles/objection, 総務課[そうむか]:general affairs section, 人事[じんじ]:personnel affairs/human affairs/human resources, 人事[ひとごと, たにんごと]:other people's affairs/somebody else's problem, なさる:to do
（ゲイハート）
苦情なら 総務課人事に行きなさい
（タナベ）
１人の人間として…
- It's as a fellow human...
直接[ちょくせつ]:direct/immediate/personal, 事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager
直接 事業部長に言いたいんです
But I want to tell the division director
in person!
In person? Who do you think you are,
you Half Section scum?
直接[ちょくせつ]:direct/immediate/personal, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（ゲイハート）
直接とは何だ この半課者
まったく:really/truly|indeed, ばかばかしい:absurd/ridiculous/silly
まったく ばかばかしい
I swear, what a bunch
of nonsense...
（タナベ）あっ ちょっと！
Hey, wait!
しつこい:insistent/obstinate|too rich (taste, etc.)
（社員）しつこいな 君も
Give it a rest,
would you?!
くっ…
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||
（クレア）無理よ
It's useless.
And what's that
supposed to mean?
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
どういう意味ですか？ それ
For someone at the bottom to defeat someone
at the top, regular tactics won't work.
勝つ[かつ]:to win/to gain victory
（クレア）
下が上に勝とうと思ったら―
正攻法[せいこうほう]:frontal attack, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
正攻法じゃ 駄目ってこと
は？
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
こ… これくらいかな？ どう？
Is this about right? How's it look?
A little more to the right, Assistant Chief.
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance, 右[みぎ]:right/right hand side|afore-mentioned (esp. in vertical Japanese writing)
（エーデル）
課長補佐 もうちょっと右です
（課長）あっ こ… こう？
あ あ あーっ…
How about now?
Are you all right?
いてる:to freeze/to be frozen over/to congeal
（エーデル）大丈夫ですか？
（課長）いてててて…
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance
課長補佐
Assistant Chief?
I'm sorry!
（課長）ごめんね…
ごめんね 何もできなくて
I'm sorry that I'm so useless!
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise)
デブリ課も守れないし―
I can't protect Debris Section, and I rely
on you to do everything for me, E-chan...
お世話になる[おせわになる]:to receive favor (favour)/to be much obliged to someone/to be indebted, っぱなし:keep ...-ing (negative nuance, with the state being improper, unpleasant, etc.)/have been ...-ing/leaving (something) on
エーちゃんにも
お世話になりっぱなしだし
Even if I tried my hardest, it's probably
too late for me to make any difference...
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 今更[いまさら]:now (after such a long time)/at this late hour (i.e. it is too late for something)|afresh, 一生懸命[いっしょうけんめい]:very hard/with utmost effort/with all one's might
駄目なんだろうね
今更 一生懸命にやろうとしても
Assistant Chief.
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance
課長補佐
老後[ろうご]:old age
どうしよう みんなの老後
What's everybody gonna
do in their old age?
ん…
珍しい[めずらしい]:unusual|new|fine (e.g. gift)
（ハチマキ）珍しいな
（タナベ）あ…
Now this is
a rare sight.
I didn't expect you to
come along, Lavie.
わざわざ:expressly/specially/doing something especially rather than incidentally, ついてくる:to follow/to come along with one/to accompany, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
ラビィが
わざわざ ついてくるなんて
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, ミッション:mission
あっ ああ
最後のミッションだから
Mark confirmed. Zulu 1024, 36, 54.
Yes, well, it's our
final mission.
役職[やくしょく]:post/managerial position/official position
役職上さ
It's part of
my duties.
Guide us in until we reach orbit
correction point. You copy?
ふーん:hmm/well ...|roughly
（ハチマキ）ふーん
I copy.
Datalink via area Navstars confirmed through Molniya orbit.
ハチマキ:headband
なあ ハチマキ
Say, Hachimaki...
サラリーマン:office worker/company employee/company man
俺たちってサラリーマンだよな
We really are corporate drones, aren't we?
今更[いまさら]:now (after such a long time)/at this late hour (i.e. it is too late for something)|afresh
（ハチマキ）何を今更
What brought
this on?
今更[いまさら]:now (after such a long time)/at this late hour (i.e. it is too late for something)|afresh
（ハチマキ）何を今更
Power transfer laser
tracking control is nominal.
救難[きゅうなん]:rescue/salvage, 信号[しんごう]:signal/signalling|traffic light
（ユーリ）あっ 救難信号？
A distress signal?
Pass me the coordinates
of their location.
位置[いち]:place/situation/position, 座標[ざひょう]:coordinate/coordinates, 回す[まわす]:to turn|to circulate|to surround||
位置座標をこっちに回して
係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 変更[へんこう]:change/modification/alteration
係長 仕事変更するけど いいよね？
Manager, I'm going to switch jobs.
That okay with you?
Sure...
ああ
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, ミッション:mission, 漂流[ひょうりゅう]:drifting/drift/being adrift, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 拾[じゅう, とお]:ten
最後のミッションは
漂流した宇宙船拾いか
So, our last mission will be rescuing
a spaceship that's adrift, huh?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise), ヒーロー:hero, ピッタリ:tightly/closely
宇宙を守るヒーローには
ピッタリだ
That's a perfect ending for
heroes who keep space safe.
Wow, that really
takes me back!
懐かしい[なつかしい]:dear/desired/missed
うわっ 懐かしいな
ライセンス:license/licence, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||, 作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
私がライセンスを取ったころの
作業船だよ
We were on a work boat like that
back when I got my license!
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 老朽[ろうきゅう]:superannuated/decrepitude, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
…てことは 20年以上の老朽船か
In other words, it's a rust bucket
that's over 20 years old, huh?
接舷[せつげん]:coming alongside (a boat, pier, etc)
（フィー）これから接舷する
Now docking. Hachimaki, you stand by
in the Fishbone as planned.
ハチマキ:headband, 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, どおり:in accordance with/following|roughly, フィッシュ:fish, ボーン:born, 待機[たいき]:alert/standby/await an opportunity
ハチマキは予定どおり
フィッシュボーンで待機して
コピー:copy/photocopy
（ハチマキ）アイ コピー
I copy.
酸素[さんそ]:oxygen (O), ボンベ:compressed gas cylinder, 準備[じゅんび]:preparation/setup/arrangements
（フィー）ユーリとタナベは
酸素ボンベの準備
Yuri and Tanabe, get some
oxygen tanks ready.
Once I've docked, get confirmation of their
shipboard status. Especially the pressure.
ドッキング:docking, 相手側[あいてがわ]:other side/other party/other end (e.g. of phone connection), 船内[せんない]:on-board ship/inboard, 状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
ドッキングしたら
相手側の船内状況の確認をして
特に[とくに]:particularly/especially, 気圧[きあつ]:atmospheric pressure
特に気圧
I copy.
コピー:copy/photocopy
（ユーリ）アイ コピー
ハッチ:hatch, 開ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 開ける[ひらける]:to become opened up|to develop|to be enlightened
（ユーリ）ハッチを開ける
Opening hatch.
ユーリさん
Yuri-san...
確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
ああ 今 確認している
Yes. I am checking
it out right now.
Fee, target ship's pressure and
air circulation are both green.
フィー:phi, 対象[たいしょう]:target/object (of worship, study, etc.)/subject (of taxation, etc.), 船内[せんない]:on-board ship/inboard, 気圧[きあつ]:atmospheric pressure, 空気[くうき]:air|mood|someone with no presence, 循環[じゅんかん]:circulation/rotation/cycle, 共[ども]:first-person plural (or singular)|second or third person plural (implies speaker is of higher status than those referred to), 共[とも]:together with|same|both|, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
フィー 対象の船内気圧 空気循環
共に問題なし
航行[こうこう]:cruise/navigation/sailing, システム:system, ダウン:down (opposite of up)/becoming lower/being brought down, 模様[もよう]:pattern|state|conjecture of the current situation||
航行システムのみが
ダウンしている模様だ
It looks like it is only their
flight system that is down.
航行[こうこう]:cruise/navigation/sailing, システム:system, ダウン:down (opposite of up)/becoming lower/being brought down, 模様[もよう]:pattern|state|conjecture of the current situation||
航行システムのみが
ダウンしている模様だ
（パイロット）だから
言ったじゃないですか
Didn't I tell you this
would happen?!
（パイロット）だから
言ったじゃないですか
船内[せんない]:on-board ship/inboard, 状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances
これから船内状況の…
Will now check out
ship's interior.
船内[せんない]:on-board ship/inboard, 状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances
これから船内状況の…
予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, 地[ち]:earth|place|territory||, 地[つち, つし]:earth|the earth (historically, esp. as opposed to the heavens)|low-quality torinoko-gami (containing mud)|, 変える[かえる]:to change/to alter|to reform
予定地を変えて―
I said that changing course and coming all the
way up into a Molniya orbit was a bad idea!
生存者[せいぞんしゃ, せいざんしゃ]:survivor
うん？ 生存者？
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
モルニア軌道まで来るのは
マズいって
Survivors?
I'm charging you for breach of contract
and repairs!
違約金[いやくきん]:penalty for contract breach, 修理[しゅうり, しゅり]:repairing/mending/servicing, 代[しろ]:substitution|material|price||, 代[よ]:world/society/age, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
（パイロット）
違約金や修理代 頼みますよ
こっちは…
（監督）何言ってんだ
I'm just a courier!
- What're you talking about?
システム:system, ダウン:down (opposite of up)/becoming lower/being brought down
（監督）俺がシステムダウン
させたわけじゃないだろ？
I wasn't
the one who crashed your systems!
システム:system, ダウン:down (opposite of up)/becoming lower/being brought down
（監督）俺がシステムダウン
させたわけじゃないだろ？
監督[かんとく]:supervision/control|director, あまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 怒る[おこる, いかる]:to get angry|to tell someone off|to be angular, マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
（ＡＤ）監督 あまり
怒らせるとマズいっすよ
- Director, don't get too
worked up.
監督[かんとく]:supervision/control|director, あまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 怒る[おこる, いかる]:to get angry|to tell someone off|to be angular, マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
（ＡＤ）監督 あまり
怒らせるとマズいっすよ
監督[かんとく]:supervision/control|director, あまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 怒る[おこる, いかる]:to get angry|to tell someone off|to be angular, マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
（ＡＤ）監督 あまり
怒らせるとマズいっすよ
大体[だいたい]:outline|general|in the first place, ボロボロ:worn-out/ragged/tattered, 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
大体 こんなボロボロで
誰が許すなんて言った
Besides, who told you to get us
a clunker like this?!
無許可[むきょか]:unauthorized/without permission|lack of permission, 監督[かんとく]:supervision/control|director
あーっ！ 無許可の監督
The unlicensed director!
ん？ 誰だ？ お前
Who are you?
It's me! We met on
the Luna Ferry!
（タナベ）
ほら ルナフェリーで会った
頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||, 幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck, ねえちゃん:elder sister/girl
（監督）
ああ 頭が幸せなねえちゃんか
Oh, that girl who had
her head in the clouds!
何だ こいつらか
Oh, it's those guys.
You really saved
our skins!
Are you filming a movie
without a permit again?
知ってる人？
You know them?
ちょっとね
Something like that.
Hey, stop talking nonsense! Me and
my crew are social activists now!
つまる:to be packed (with)/to be full (space, schedule, etc.)|to be blocked (road, pipe, etc.), 出会い[であい]:meeting/rendezvous|confluence
つまんない出会いでさ… おっ？
We bumped into them when... Huh?
おーい:hey!/oi!|I, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
（ハチマキ）
おーい 俺 戻っていいかな？
Hey!
Can I come back in now? There wasn't any serious trouble, right?
問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 特に[とくに]:particularly/especially
問題は特になかったんだろう？
（フィー）待って ハチ
（ハチマキ）あ？
Hang on, Hachi.
相対[あいたい]:confrontation/facing/between ourselves, 相対[そうたい]:relativity|relative, 速度[そくど]:speed/velocity/rate, ほとんど:mostly/nearly/practically, デブリ:debris
（フィー）相対速度が
ほとんどゼロのデブリがある
There's some debris out there with
a relative velocity of about zero.
We can't look this gift horse in the mouth,
now can we?
偶然[ぐうぜん]:coincidence|by chance|contingency (philosophy), 見過ごす[みすごす]:to let go by/to let pass/to overlook
こんな偶然
見過ごす手はないと思わない？
Anyway, it's our last job.
どうせ:anyhow/in any case|at best, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
どうせ最後の仕事なんだしさ
Sure, why not?
まあ いいけど
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
（パイロット）すいません 会社に
連絡 入れとかないとマズいんで
I'm sorry, but I should really
check in with my company.
いいですよ
Sure, go ahead. Use the comm system
in our residential block.
居住区[きょじゅうく]:residential area/quarter/neighbourhood, 通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, システム:system, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
居住区の通信システムを
使ってください
（パイロット）すいません どうも
Thanks, I appreciate it.
（監督）おっ
修理[しゅうり, しゅり]:repairing/mending/servicing, 代[しろ]:substitution|material|price||, 代[よ]:world/society/age, まける:to lose/to be defeated|to succumb, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（ＡＤ）修理代 まけてくださいね
Cut us a deal on the
repair costs, okay?
（パイロット）知るか
The hell I will!
Anyway, I sold that movie I shot
on the Luna Ferry for a bundle,
ムービー:movie, 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive, 売れる[うれる]:to sell (well)|to be well known/to be popular
（監督）…で ルナフェリーでの
ムービーが高く売れてさ
報道[ほうどう]:information/report|to report, 転身[てんしん]:(job) turnover, 図る[はかる]:to plan|to plot|to aim for|
報道に転身 図ったわけ
...so I tried to get
into journalism.
やっぱり:too/also|still, 金儲け[かねもうけ]:money-making
なんだ
やっぱり お金儲けじゃないですか
I knew it, you're still in it
for the money, aren't you?
（監督）何言ってんだ
What're you talking about?
I'll suddenly be happy if I'm poor?
貧乏[びんぼう]:poverty/destitute/poor, 不幸[ふこう]:unhappiness/sorrow|death (usu. of a relative), 幸福[こうふく]:happiness/blessedness/joy, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
貧乏なら
不幸が幸福に変わるってのかよ
I'm just saying that your
motives are corrupt!
動機[どうき]:motive/incentive|motif, 不純[ふじゅん]:impurity/adulteration/dishonesty
だから 動機が不純だと…
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
（フィー）駄目って どうして？
- We can't grab it? Why not?!
は？
（管制官）ですから―
We're saying that we don't want you to retrieve
the debris that you contacted us about!
連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|, 対象[たいしょう]:target/object (of worship, study, etc.)/subject (of taxation, etc.), デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
連絡のあった対象デブリは
回収しないでいただきたい
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule
（フィー）
他の会社の回収予定に入ってるの？
Is it on some other company's
retrieval checklist?
I say again, DS-12 is not to attempt retrieval,
and is to return to base at once.
繰り返す[くりかえす]:to repeat/to do something over again
（管制官）
繰り返します DS-12は―
対象[たいしょう]:target/object (of worship, study, etc.)/subject (of taxation, etc.), デブリ:debris, 触れる[ふれる]:to touch|to experience|to touch on a subject||, 直ちに[ただちに]:at once/immediately/directly, 帰投[きとう]:return to base of soldiers, military aircraft or ships, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
対象デブリに触れず
直ちに帰投してください
コピー:copy/photocopy
ユー コピー？
You copy?
理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive
はあ？ だから理由を…
Huh? At least give me
a reason!
理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive
はあ？ だから理由を…
切る[きる]:to cut|to sever (connections, ties)|to turn off (e.g. the light)||, 今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, 担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.), 管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic)
切っちゃったよ おい
何だ？ 今度の担当管制官
The jerk hung up
on me.
What's with this new Control supervisor
they gave us?
監督[かんとく]:supervision/control|director, やっぱ:too/also|still, 機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine
（ＡＤ）ほらほら 監督
やっぱ 機雷っすよ
See? I knew it, Director! It's gotta be a mine!
A mine?
機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine
機雷！？
There have been rumors that INTO has been
laying mines disguised as debris up here.
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), デブリ:debris, 見せかける[みせかける]:to pretend/to feign
連合はデブリに見せかけて―
機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine, 浮かべる[うかべる]:to float|to show on one's face (smile, sadness, etc.)|to recall, うわさ:rumour/rumor/report
機雷を浮かべてるって
うわさがあってね
We came up here to expose
what they're doing.
そいつ:he/she|that, 暴く[あばく]:to disclose/to divulge|to open (and rob) a grave
俺たちはそいつを暴くために
来たってわけだ
爆弾[ばくだん, バクダン]:bomb|alcohol with liquor added (esp. wine-based shochu highball, also beer with whiskey)
じゃあ あれ 爆弾なんですか？
Is it some kind
of bomb, then?
Not exactly. They call it
a "data mine."
データ:data/datum, 機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine
ちょっと違う
あれはデータ機雷とかいってな
When a ship comes close,
it burns out its flight systems.
近づく[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 航行[こうこう]:cruise/navigation/sailing, システム:system, 焼く[やく]:to burn|to roast|to heat||
近づいた船の航行システムを
焼いちまうんだ
作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
（ユーリ）
じゃあ あなたたちの作業船が―
Oh, so that is what crashed
your work ship's systems.
システム:system, ダウン:down (opposite of up)/becoming lower/being brought down
システムダウンしたのは…
名目[めいもく, みょうもく]:name/title|(under the) pretext (of), デブリ:debris
（監督）ああ あれは名目上
デブリってなってるだけさ
Yeah. It's listed as debris,
but it's anything but.
I can't believe dangerous things
like that are floating in space!
危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 浮かぶ[うかぶ]:to float|to rise to surface|to come to mind, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
そんな危ないものが
宇宙に浮かんでるなんて
当然[とうぜん]:natural/as a matter of course/justified, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||, おける:in/at/for
当然 放っておけないよな
Needless to say, we can't leave
that thing out there.
フィー:phi, まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected
フィー君 まさか
Fee-kun, you aren't seriously
going to...
ロシア:Russia, 緊急[きんきゅう]:urgency/emergency, 避難[ひなん]:taking refuge/finding shelter/evacuation, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, でもある:to also be (formal, literary)/implies that as well as the earlier stated this is also the case|to be ... or something
ここは ロシアやＥＵの
緊急避難用軌道でもあるし
Besides, this is an emergency evacuation
orbit used by Russia and the EU.
（ラビィ）ちょっと…
Hey!
If INTO is claiming it's just debris, then they
can't complain if we go pick it up, right?
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), デブリ:debris, 言い張る[いいはる]:to insist/to assert/to be obstinate in saying
（フィー）連合が
デブリって言い張るのなら―
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 文句[もんく]:complaint/grumbling|phrase, 言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say
私たちが回収しても
文句 言えないだろ
（タナベ）そうですよね
Yeah, right!
待つ[まつ]:to wait|to await|to depend on, 管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
（ラビィ）待てよ
管制課が駄目って言ってるんだ
Wait! If Control Section says we can't,
then as loyal employees, we have to...
サラリーマン:office worker/company employee/company man
サラリーマンなら…
人命[じんめい]:(human) life, 懸かる[かかる]:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang|to come into view||
人命が懸かっているんですよ！
Lives are
at stake here!
あ…
It probably works by detecting changes
in the communications data environment.
恐らく[おそらく]:perhaps/likely/probably
（ユーリ）恐らく―
通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 環境[かんきょう]:environment/circumstance, 変化[へんか]:change|variety|inflection|, 変化[へんげ]:shapeshifting (of an animal or spirit)|incarnation|transformation, 認識[にんしき]:recognition/awareness/perception, タイプ:type/kind/sort
通信情報環境の変化を
認識するタイプだな
So it would react to
our Fishbones, too?
フィッシュ:fish, ボーン:born
（フィー）じゃあ
フィッシュボーンでも―
反応[はんのう, はんおう]:reaction/response
反応するってこと？
One person will have to go solo in a spacesuit
with its face-computer shut off.
カット:cut/cutting, 宇宙服[うちゅうふく]:space suit
（ユーリ）フェイスコムを
カットした宇宙服―
身[み]:body|oneself|one's place|, 身[むくろ]:(dead) body/corpse
身ひとつで行くしかない
But we don't have a lifeline
that'll reach that far!
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals, 届く[とどく]:to reach|to be attentive|to be delivered, 命綱[いのちづな]:lifeline, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（タナベ）でも あそこまで届く
命綱なんてないですよ
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||
（ラビィ）
無理だよ 誰もできっこないって
It's hopeless! I'm telling you,
nobody could possibly do that!
I'll go.
（ハチマキ）俺が行く
Senpai?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩？
Weren't you listening, Hachimaki?
ハチマキ:headband
聞いてなかったのか？ ハチマキ
This is an S-class EVA
we're talking about!
クラス:class
こいつは
ＳクラスのＥＶＡなんだぞ
（ハチマキ）だから行くんだ
That's why I'm going.
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
これくらいできなきゃ
I have to be able to handle
something like this...
フィー:phi
分かった
（ラビィ）フィー君
Understood.
Fee-kun!
Tanabe, prep some spare
oxygen tanks for me!
増設[ぞうせつ]:extension/expansion/adding (equipment, facilities, etc.), ボンベ:compressed gas cylinder, 用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision
（ハチマキ）タナベ
増設ボンベを用意しろ
は… はい！
R-Right!
画[かく]:stroke (of a kanji, etc.), 画[が, え]:picture/drawing/painting, 撮れる[とれる]:to be photographed|to be able to photograph
こいつは いい画(え)が撮れそうだ
This is gonna make for
some awesome footage...
But this is Debris Section's last day.
You don't have to try so hard...
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place, たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however
今日で デブリ課は最後なんだ
そんなに頑張らなくたってさ
機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine, 人力[じんりき, じんりょく]:human power/human strength/human effort, 壊す[こわす]:to break|to wreck|to break (a bill, etc.)
（タナベ）あっ でも機雷って
人力で壊せるんですか？
But can we destroy
the mine manually?
コネクター:connector, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
（ユーリ）
コネクターを持っていってもらおう
I'll have him take a connector along.
We can feed it false data through the Navstar.
ナブスター:Navstar, 経由[けいゆ, けいゆう]:through/by way of|to go via, 機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine, 情報[じょうほう]:information/news|information, 伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
ナブスター経由で
機雷に うその情報を伝えればいい
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（ラビィ）やめろよ
Don't do it!
独りぼっち[ひとりぼっち, ひとりぽっち]:aloneness/loneliness/solitude, 浮かぶ[うかぶ]:to float|to rise to surface|to come to mind
（タナベ）独りぼっちで
浮かんでいると思わせるんですか
Oh, we're going to make it think that it's
floating out there all alone, huh?
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（ラビィ）やめろって
I said, don't do this!
だまし:deceiving/cheating/fooling, 近づける[ちかづける]:to bring near/to put close/to let come near
（フィー）
だましさえすれば近づけるからな
If we can manage to fool it,
we can close in.
Then we hit it with Toy Box's
arm until it stops working.
アーム:arm, 機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine, 機能[きのう]:function/facility/faculty, たたき壊す[たたきこわす]:to tear down/to shatter
あとは ToyBox(トイボックス)のアームで
機雷の機能をたたき壊す
Please, don't do this...
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
やめてくれ
Hachimaki, did you
get all that?
ハチマキ:headband, 聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
（フィー）ハチマキ 聞こえてた？
Yeah. Find out where the connecter hooks up.
I'm gonna make this work...
（ハチマキ）ああ
コネクター:connector, 取り付け[とりつけ]:installation/mounting|run (on a bank), 位置[いち]:place/situation/position, 探る[さぐる]:to feel around for|to investigate|to explore (parts unknown)
コネクターの取り付け位置を
探ってくれ
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness, 成功[せいこう]:success/hit
絶対に成功させて…
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
やめろーっ！
（ハチマキ）あ？
I SAID STOP!
社会[しゃかい]:society/public|social studies, 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely
ラビィ
テクノーラが社会の全てじゃ…
Lavie, there's more to
the world than Technora.
分かってる！ けど…
I know that!
But...
いちばん:number one/first|best, 頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||
あの… いちばん上のコラナは
頭のいい子でさ
Well... My oldest, Khorana, is a bright girl.
I want to send her to a private school if I can.
私立[しりつ, わたくしりつ]:private (establishment)
できれば私立に行かせてやりたい
Haal loves space, and said that
she wanted a telescope.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to), 望遠鏡[ぼうえんきょう]:telescope, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
ハールは宇宙が好きで
望遠鏡が欲しいって言うんだ
幼い[おさない, いとけない]:very young|childish/immature, 音楽[おんがく]:music/musical movement, 才能[さいのう]:talent/ability
ムシャラフは まだ幼いけど
音楽の才能があって―
Musharraf is
still little,
...but he's got a gift for music, so I want
to get him sitar or piano lessons.
シタール:sitar, ピアノ:piano, 習わす[ならわす]:to make (someone) learn
シタールかピアノを
習わせてやりたい
I can't be with them as
their father anymore,
父親[ちちおや]:father
私は もう父親として
そばにいてやれないから―
...so all I can do now
is earn money for them.
お金[おかね]:money, 稼ぐ[かせぐ]:to earn (income)|to score (points, victory)|to work hard (at one's job), ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
お金を稼ぐぐらいしか
できることは…
頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|
頼むよ 頼むよ みんな
So please...
Please, everyone!
I can't afford
to be fired!
クビになる:to be sacked/to be fired|to be beheaded
私は クビになるわけには
いかないんだ
増設[ぞうせつ]:extension/expansion/adding (equipment, facilities, etc.), ボンベ:compressed gas cylinder, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 届ける[とどける]:to deliver/to forward|to report
（フィー）
タナベ 増設ボンベを早く届けな
Tanabe, get those spare
oxygen tanks to him ASAP.
コピー:copy/photocopy
（タナベ）ア… アイ コピー
I-I copy!
フィー:phi
フィー君！
（フィー）言っただろ
Fee-kun!
Weren't you listening? Technora might
be a company, but it isn't the whole world.
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 社会[しゃかい]:society/public|social studies
テクノーラは
会社であっても社会じゃない
Besides, even if Debris Section
is going to be disbanded,
たとえ:example|simile/metaphor, たとえ:even if/no matter (what)/if, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 解散[かいさん]:breakup/dissolution
そして たとえデブリ課が
解散するとしても―
...right here and now,
we're still debris haulers!
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
私たちは まだデブリ屋なんだ
業務[ぎょうむ]:business/affairs/duties, 資料[しりょう]:materials/data/document, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments
（社員）
業務資料は これで最後ですね
These are the last of the official
documents, then?
多分[たぶん]:perhaps/probably|generous
はい 多分
Yes, I think so...
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 船外[せんがい]:outboard/extra-vehicular, 活動[かつどう]:action/activity|movie (esp. during the silent movie period), 員[いん]:member
（管制官）課長 DS-12が
船外活動員を出すようです
Chief!
It looks like the DS-12 is going
to send out an EVA worker!
I told you to stop them,
didn't I?!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, させる:to make (someone) do|to allow (someone) to, させる:(usu. followed by a negative form) worth special consideration
（ゲイハート）
やめさせろと言っただろう？
Can't you even train your men
to obey orders?!
部下[ぶか]:subordinate person, 教育[きょういく]:training/education
部下の教育もできんのか
（課長）すいません
I'm sorry!
騒ぐ[さわぐ]:to make noise|to rustle|to make merry||
（ノーマン）騒ぐな
（ゲイハート）はっ
Calm down.
非常[ひじょう]:emergency|extraordinary/unusual, 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person, システム:system, 済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
（ノーマン）
非常停止システムを使えば済む話だ
We just need to use the emergency
shutdown system, and that'll be that.
（課長）えっ 何ですか？
What's that?
全体[ぜんたい]:whole/entirety/whatever (is the matter), 会議[かいぎ]:meeting/conference/session, 資料[しりょう]:materials/data/document, 把握[はあく]:grasp/catch/understanding, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
君は 全体会議の資料すら
把握していないようだな
I see you don't follow the material
from our general meetings.
対[たい]:opposite|versus|to (e.g. "winning a game five to three")||, 対[つい]:pair|antithesis|counter for items that come in pairs|, テロリスト:terrorist, 用[よう]:business|use|for the use of ...|, セキュリティー:security
対テロリスト用の
セキュリティーとして―
As part of our anti-terrorism
security measures,
我が社[わがしゃ]:our company/my company, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship
我が社の宇宙船には―
...every one of our ships has been fitted with a
device that allows us to shut it down from here.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person, 機能[きのう]:function/facility/faculty, 付け加える[つけくわえる]:to add one thing to another
こちらから停止させる機能を
付け加えてあるだろう
デブリ:debris, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather
でも 彼らは
デブリを拾おうとしているだけで
But they're only trying to pick up
a piece of debris!
マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
あれはマズいんだよ
We can't let them
do that.
どうして？
（ゲイハート）それは…
Why not?
Well... I don't need to explain
myself to you.
説明[せつめい]:explanation/exposition, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
（ノーマン）説明の必要などない
番[ばん]:number (in a series)|(one's) turn|watch|, 番[つがい]:(one) pair (e.g. of birds)/brace|joint
さあ 君の番だ
All right, now it's
your turn.
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager, 担当[たんとう]:being in charge (of an area of responsibility)/being responsible (for a work role, etc.), 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 承認[しょうにん]:recognition/acknowledgement/acknowledgment, プログラム:program/programme, 発動[はつどう]:putting into operation|invocation
事業部長と担当課長の承認で
プログラムは発動される
The program will activate once approved by the division director and the head of the relevant section.
パスワード:(computer) password, ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|
ＩＤパスワードぐらい
覚えているだろう
You can at least remember your
own ID password, can't you?
パスワード:(computer) password, ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|
ＩＤパスワードぐらい
覚えているだろう
ううう…
Do you think Senpai's
gonna be okay?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩 大丈夫でしょうか？
（ハチマキ）ハァ ハァ ハァ…
An S-class EVA... I have to be
able to do at least this much.
クラス:class, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
（ハチマキ）ＳクラスのＥＶＡ
これくらいやれないと
Hurry up and input your code,
you scum!
とっとと:quickly/at once/right away
とっととやれ このクズが
あの…
Um...
This will shut down Toy Box, won't it?
止まる[とまる]:to stop (moving)|to stop (doing, working, being supplied)|to alight, 止まる[とどまる]:to remain/to abide|to be limited to
止まっちゃうんですよね
ToyBox
I mean, this is
their last job and all...
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
最後の仕事ですし
それがどうした
What about it?
Um...
その…
忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of, 暗証番号[あんしょうばんごう]:personal identification number/PIN/password number
ああっ
忘れちゃいました 暗証番号
I forgot it! I forgot my security code.
ふざける:to joke/to jest|to make fun of
ふざけるな！
（課長）ひいっ
Stop fooling around!
I'm so sorry, I've always been
the forgetful type!
もともと:originally/by nature/from the start, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of, っぽい:-ish/-like|tossing something out
すいませんね
もともと忘れっぽいたちでして
定年[ていねん]:retirement age|years of service in a military rank before eligibility for promotion, めっきり:remarkably, 記憶[きおく]:memory/recollection|storage
もうすぐ定年ですし
めっきり記憶が…
Plus, I'm about to retire, and my
memory's getting noticeably worse.
誕生日[たんじょうび]:birthday, 結婚[けっこん]:marriage, 記念日[きねんび]:holiday/anniversary/memorial day
誕生日だったかな？
それとも結婚記念日？
Maybe it was
my birthday...
Or maybe my
wedding anniversary!
（ハチマキ）
ハァ ハァ ハァ ハァ…
相対[あいたい]:confrontation/facing/between ourselves, 相対[そうたい]:relativity|relative, 速度[そくど]:speed/velocity/rate
相対速度が…
My relative velocity's too...
Almost there!
一息[ひといき]:one breath|one go (i.e. in a short time)|small amount of effort
もう一息 なんとか…
Have to... grab on!
お前は…
やった
I did it?
ああ… 俺は…
I...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
やりましたよ 先輩が
Senpai did it!
ほんと:truth/reality|proper, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
まっさか ほんとにできるなんてね
I wouldn't believe it if I hadn't
seen it with my own eyes.
Hey, that guy's
pretty good!
おお やるなあ 彼
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（ゲイハート）この半課者が！
You Half Section lowlife! Quit your faking,
you're not fooling anybody!
わざと:on purpose, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish, 芝居[しばい]:play/drama, 打つ[うつ]:to hit|to strike (noon, etc.)|to beat (rhythmically, e.g. pulse, waves, etc.)||, 打つ[ぶつ]:to hit (a person)/to strike/to beat
わざとらしい芝居を
打っているんじゃない！
ああっ 本当なんです
It's the truth!
もういい
（ゲイハート）あっ…
Enough.
Navstar connection
status is nominal.
ナブスター:Navstar, 接続[せつぞく]:connection|changing trains|conjunction, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation, 良好[りょうこう]:favorable/favourable/satisfactory
（ユーリ）
ナブスターとの接続状態 良好
Okay, we fooled
the mine!
機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine, だます:to trick/to cheat|to coax
（フィー）よし！ 機雷をだました
Center of mass
is stable.
重心[じゅうしん]:centre of gravity (center)|centroid|(one's) balance, 安定[あんてい]:stability/steadiness/equilibrium
重心は安定
I copy. Leave the
rest to me.
コピー:copy/photocopy, 任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||
（フィー）アイ コピー
あとはこっちに任せて
コピー:copy/photocopy, 任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||
（フィー）アイ コピー
あとはこっちに任せて
ナブスター:Navstar, アクセス:access, 拒否[きょひ]:denial/veto/rejection
ナブスターが
アクセスを拒否してる
Navstar's denying access?
（フィー）あっ…
機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine, だませる:to trick/to cheat|to coax
それじゃ
機雷をだませないじゃないか
But that means we won't
be able to fool the mine!
諦める[あきらめる]:to give up/to abandon (hope, plans)/to resign oneself (to), 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（ノーマン）諦めろ 半課ども
Give it up, you Half Section halfwits.
I've cut your Navstar access from here.
Your little ploy ends here.
ナブスター:Navstar, 接続[せつぞく]:connection|changing trains|conjunction, こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), カット:cut/cutting
ナブスターとの接続は
こちらでカットした
小細工[こざいく]:tricks/artfulness
君たちの小細工も ここまでだ
Leave that orbit
right now.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 離れる[はなれる]:to be separated|to leave|to leave (a job, etc.)|
今すぐに その軌道を離れろ
If you don't do it quickly, DS-12's systems might
be fried, and you'll end up dead in space, too.
急ぐ[いそぐ]:to hurry/to rush/to hasten
急がねば―
システム:system, 漂流[ひょうりゅう]:drifting/drift/being adrift, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
DS-12も システムをやられて
漂流することになる
もっとも:most/extremely, もっとも:but then/although|reasonable, 間に合う[まにあう]:to be in time for|to serve (suit, meet) the purpose/to be good enough, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
ハハッ もっとも
もう間に合わんかもしれんがな
Of course, maybe it's
already too late.
（ハチマキ）くっ…
Hey! What do you mean,
dead in space?
漂流[ひょうりゅう]:drifting/drift/being adrift
ちょっと 漂流って何ですか
You aren't saying that they're
all going to die, are you?!
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance, じゃう:to do something completely
もしかして
みんな死んじゃうようなことを
Let go of me!
離す[はなす]:to separate/to part/to divide
離したまえ
I'm begging you! Anything but that!
願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
（課長）
お願いします それだけは
I don't need trash like Debris Section
in my division!
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
デブリ課なんてゴミはな
私の事業部には必要ないんだ！
あたる:to be hit/to strike|to touch, 課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance
（課長）あたっ ああっ…
（エーデル）課長補佐
Assistant Chief!
まったく:really/truly|indeed, デブリ:debris
（ノーマン）まったく…
デブリのほうが まだマシだ
I swear, give me debris
any day.
リサイクル:recycling, 金になる[かねになる]:profitable/lucrative
お前らと違って
リサイクルして金になるからな
We can recycle debris and make money
off it, unlike you people.
なあ？
Right?
ううっ うっ ううう…
Junk jockeys being set adrift and becoming
debris themselves is poetic justice!
デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 漂流[ひょうりゅう]:drifting/drift/being adrift, 自業自得[じごうじとく]:paying for one's mistakes/getting one's just deserts/suffering the consequences (of one's own actions)
デブリ屋が漂流して
デブリになるのも 自業自得
Now that I'm division
director, I'll...
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager
私が事業部長になったからには…
事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
（課長）
あんたの事業部に必要なくても―
Even if you don't need us in your division,
the human race needs us!
人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
人類には必要なんだーっ！
非常[ひじょう]:emergency|extraordinary/unusual, 電源[でんげん]:source of electricity/electrical power|power (button on TV, etc.)
あっ 非常電源に
We just went to
emergency power!
What happened? Did the mine get you?!
（ハチマキ）
どうした？ やられたか
Yeah, but our communications and life
support systems seem to be working.
通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 維持[いじ]:maintenance/preservation/improvement, 系[けい]:system|corollary|system (range of strata that correspond to a particular time period)|
（フィー）ああ
でも 通信と生命維持系はなんとか
I copy! I'll fiddle with the mine's systems
and try to do something on this end.
コピー:copy/photocopy
（ハチマキ）アイ コピー
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine, システム:system, いじる:to touch/to tamper with|to grope about
こちらでなんとか
機雷のシステムをいじってみる
（ノーマン）うおーっ
（課長）うっ ううっ
You bastard!
How dare you lay your hands
on the division director?!
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager
（ゲイハート）
ああっ 事業部長に何を
勤務時間[きんむじかん]:office (business, working) hours, 終了[しゅうりょう]:end/close/termination
勤務時間は終了しました
My work hours
just ended.
派遣社員[はけんしゃいん]:temporary employee (esp. from an agency)/temporary worker/agency temp
今の私は テクノーラの
派遣社員ではないと言ったんです
That means that right now, I'm no longer
a temp worker under contract to Technora!
（殴る音）
（ゲイハート）うおっ
（管制官たち）おっ？
Hey, Half Section's going
crazy up there!
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 暴れる[あばれる]:to act violently/to rage/to struggle
（管制官１）
おい 半課が暴れてるぞ
管制官[かんせいかん]:controller (usually air-traffic), 警備員[けいびいん]:guard/security (officer)/guardsman
（管制官２）誰か 警備員
Somebody! Call security!
人殺し[ひとごろし]:murder/murderer
（課長）この人殺し！
You murderer! If they don't pick up debris,
space development will stop in its tracks!
デブリ:debris, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, 進む[すすむ]:to advance|to precede|to make progress||, 進む[すさむ]:to grow wild/to run to waste
みんながデブリを拾わなきゃ
宇宙開発は 進まないんだぞ！
今更[いまさら]:now (after such a long time)/at this late hour (i.e. it is too late for something)|afresh, 課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief
（ノーマン）何を今更…
（フィー）やるね 課長
Who do you think you are?
Security, clean up this trash!
- That's telling him, Chief.
今更[いまさら]:now (after such a long time)/at this late hour (i.e. it is too late for something)|afresh, 課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief
（ノーマン）何を今更…
（フィー）やるね 課長
警備員[けいびいん]:guard/security (officer)/guardsman, 片づける[かたづける]:to tidy up|to settle (problem)|to finish||
（ゲイハート）警備員
このゴミどもを片づけろ
警備員[けいびいん]:guard/security (officer)/guardsman, 片づける[かたづける]:to tidy up|to settle (problem)|to finish||
（ゲイハート）警備員
このゴミどもを片づけろ
手を出す[てをだす]:to turn one's hand to|to get involved in|to start a fight
（エーデル）手を出すな！
Keep your hands off me! Come any closer,
and I'll sue you for sexual harassment!
（タナベ）エーデル
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 近づく[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with, セクハラ:sexual harassment, 訴える[うったえる]:to raise|to appeal to (reason, emotions, etc.)|to complain||
これ以上 近づいたら
セクハラで訴えるよ
- Edel...
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 近づく[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with, セクハラ:sexual harassment, 訴える[うったえる]:to raise|to appeal to (reason, emotions, etc.)|to complain||
これ以上 近づいたら
セクハラで訴えるよ
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 近づく[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with, セクハラ:sexual harassment, 訴える[うったえる]:to raise|to appeal to (reason, emotions, etc.)|to complain||
これ以上 近づいたら
セクハラで訴えるよ
返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
（課長）みんなを返して
Give me back my people!
Fee-san! Yu-chan!
返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|
（課長）みんなを返して
フィー:phi, 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
フィーさん ユーちゃん ハッちゃん
愛(あい)ちゃん ラビィちゃーん
Ha-chan! Ai-chan! Lavie-chan!
うるさい:noisy/loud|annoying, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（ゲイハート）
うるさい！ この半課者が
Shut up, you Half Section halfwit!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 捕まえる[つかまえる]:to catch/to arrest/to seize
（ノーマン）
早く こいつらを捕まえろ！
Hurry up and grab
these two!
Right here and now,
Debris Section is hereby disbanded!
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 場[ば]:place|field|occasion||, 場[じょう]:place/spot/grounds, 解散[かいさん]:breakup/dissolution
デブリ課は 今 この場で解散だ！
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise)
じゃあ 誰が宇宙を守るの？
Who's gonna keep
space safe, then?
You keep space safe,
don't you, Dad?
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise)
お父さんは
宇宙を守ってるんでしょ？
Everybody says that spaceships can go into
space because you pick up debris, Daddy.
子供[こども]:child/children, お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, デブリ:debris, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 通る[とおる]:to go by|to run (between)|to go indoors||
（子供２）
お父さんがデブリを拾ってるから
宇宙船が通れるって
デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, カッコ:parentheses/brackets, カッコ:shape/form/figure
デブリ屋のほうが カッコいいよ！
It's cooler to be
a debris hauler!
ベイビー:baby
ＯＫ ベイビー
Okay, baby...
（フィー）
おい ラビィ どこ行くんだよ
Hey! Lavie, where
are you going?
（ユーリ）ラビィさん
Lavie-san!
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit
（課長）
やめて そこ こそばいの
Please! Stop! I'm ticklish there!
相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.), タイマン:one to one (battle, competition, etc.), 張る[はる]:to stick|to stretch|to form (e.g. ice on a pond)||, 張る[ばる]:to be prominently .../to be persistently ...
（エーデル）あんた 女を相手に
タイマン 張れねえってのか
What's the matter?
You're holding
back because I'm woman?
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 軍用[ぐんよう]:for military use, 頑丈[がんじょう]:solid/firm/stout
くっ さすが軍用 頑丈だな
That's a military bird for you...
This thing's built tough.
Fee-san! Our emergency power's only
gonna last another ten minutes!
フィー:phi, 非常[ひじょう]:emergency|extraordinary/unusual, 電源[でんげん]:source of electricity/electrical power|power (button on TV, etc.)
フィーさん 非常電源が
あと10分しか もちません
アーム:arm, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
アームは動かせない
I can't get the arm to work. We don't
have any way to smash the mine.
機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine, システム:system, 破壊[はかい]:destruction/disruption|(application) crash, 手段[しゅだん]:means/way/measure
もう機雷のシステムを
破壊する手段が…
分かった ここまでだな
All right, I get it. I guess that's that.
Fee-san...
フィー:phi
フィーさん
乗員[じょういん]:crew, 安全[あんぜん]:safety|security, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise), 船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
乗員の安全を守るのも
船長の仕事… おっ
Ensuring the safety of her crew
is part of a captain's...
乗員[じょういん]:crew, 安全[あんぜん]:safety|security, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise), 船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
乗員の安全を守るのも
船長の仕事… おっ
アーム:arm, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||
アーム 動かせたんですか？
Did you get
the arm working?!
システム:system, ダウン:down (opposite of up)/becoming lower/being brought down
いや
システムはダウンしたままで…
No, that system
is still down...
What did you people
do this time?!
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently
（パイロット）
あんたら今度は何やった？
（監督）知らねえって
Don't look at me! We've got
our hands full with filming!
撮影[さつえい]:photography (still or motion)/photographing/filming, 手いっぱい[ていっぱい]:having one's hands full/not having any room to do more/at the limit
こっちは
撮影で手いっぱいなんだからよ
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
まさか 作業船でラビィが…
Wait, don't tell me Lavie is over
in the work ship, and he...
システム:system, ダウン:down (opposite of up)/becoming lower/being brought down
えっ でも
システムダウンしてるんじゃ…
But aren't their
systems down, too?
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
そうか 20年以上前の船だから―
Oh, I get it! That ship
is over 20 years old,
...so the arm can be operated manually,
just like on the old Toy Box!
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
前のToyBoxと同じで―
アーム:arm, マニュアル:manual, 操作[そうさ]:operation/management|manipulating to one's benefit, 動かす[うごかす]:to move|to inspire|to change||
アームなら
マニュアル操作でも動かせる
Let's see... It's in hydraulic mode right now,
so I need to return it to neutral, and...
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ..., モード:mode (musical mode, mode of probability distribution, state of physical system), ハイドロ:hydro, 切り替える[きりかえる]:to change/to exchange/to convert
（ラビィ）えーっと モードは
ハイドロに切り替えてあるから―
ニュートラル:neutral, 戻す[もどす]:to put back|to vomit|to recover (of a market price)
ニュートラルに戻して
ぶったたく:to beat vigorously/to rain strikes upon someone/to tan someone's hide
（ハチマキ）ラビィ ここだ！
ここをぶったたけ！
Lavie! Over here! Smash it over here!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 本気[ほんき]:seriousness/earnestness/truth, ヤバい:dangerous|awful|terrific
早くしないと本気でヤバい
Do it soon, or we're
in serious trouble!
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
聞こえてんのか？ おい！
Do you read me?! Hey!
ああ 分かった
I've got it!
宴会[えんかい]:party/banquet/reception, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
（ノーマン）
いや 分かってないな 宴会屋
No, I don't think you do,
entertainment boy.
宴会[えんかい]:party/banquet/reception, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
（ノーマン）
いや 分かってないな 宴会屋
（ラビィ）うっ
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 出世[しゅっせ]:success in life/getting ahead/successful career, どころ:particle used to indicate that what precedes it is an extreme example and strongly negates it, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
（ノーマン）やめないと
出世どころか会社にも残れないぞ
If you don't stop this, you won't be
moving up, you'll be moving out.
やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, 出世[しゅっせ]:success in life/getting ahead/successful career, どころ:particle used to indicate that what precedes it is an extreme example and strongly negates it, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
（ノーマン）やめないと
出世どころか会社にも残れないぞ
（ラビィ）あっ
総務[そうむ]:general affairs/general business/manager, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, してやる:to do for (someone), 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
総務の係長にしてやると言ったのを
忘れたのか！
総務[そうむ]:general affairs/general business/manager, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, してやる:to do for (someone), 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
総務の係長にしてやると言ったのを
忘れたのか！
Have you forgotten that I said I'd make
you manager of General Affairs Section?
総務[そうむ]:general affairs/general business/manager, 係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, してやる:to do for (someone), 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
総務の係長にしてやると言ったのを
忘れたのか！
（フィー･タナベ）え？
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely
お前たちにとっては
会社が全てだろ！
The company is all you people
have, am I right?
If you defy the company
and get thrown out,
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 逆らう[さからう]:to go against/to oppose/to disobey, 放り出す[ほうりだす]:to throw out|to drop|to abandon|, 放り出す[ひりだす]:to expel/to eject/to push out, 居る[いる]:to be (of animate objects)|to stay|verb indicating continuing action or state (i.e. to be ..ing, to have been ..ing), 居る[おる]:to be (animate)|verb indicating continuing action or state (i.e. to be ..ing)|indicates contempt or disdain for another's actions, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost)
会社に逆らって放り出されて
どこに居場所を探すつもりだ！
...who else is going to give you
a place where you can belong?!
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
そうなんですよね
会社人としては分かるんですよ
Yes, I suppose that's true.
As a company man, I understand that.
でも…
But...
居場所[いばしょ]:whereabouts/place|place where one belongs
私の居場所
the place I belong...
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
フッ フフフ… 駄目だなあ 私は
I just can't win, can I?
No matter what I do, I'll...
何をやっても
せめて:at least/at most, せめて:offense/offence/method of attack
だから せめて―
So at least I can be...
At least Daddy can be...
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa
お父さんは… お父さんは…
At least your Daddy...
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise), デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
宇宙を守るデブリ屋なんだーっ！
can be a debris
hauler who keeps space safe!
（タナベ）やったー！
He did it!
ナイス:nice
（監督）うん ナイス
Nice!
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
DS-12が戻った！？
The DS-12 is
back online?!
うわーい！
（ノーマン）んんっ
Yahoo!
Oh. Um. I finally remembered it. My code, I mean.
やっと:at last/at length|barely, 思い出す[おもいだす]:to recall/to remember/to recollect, 暗証番号[あんしょうばんごう]:personal identification number/PIN/password number
あっ や… やっと思い出したんで
暗証番号 アハッ
ハハハ:ha ha ha (laughter)
（ラビィ）
ハハハ… やっちまった
I went and did it
this time...
目標[めじるし]:mark/sign/landmark, 目標[もくひょう]:mark/objective/target, デブリ:debris, 機能[きのう]:function/facility/faculty, 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
（ユーリ）
目標デブリの機能停止を確認
System shutdown of target
debris confirmed.
Nicely done, Father.
おとうさん:father/dad/papa
やりましたね おとうさん
見直す[みなおす]:to look again|to re-examine (policy, estimate, plan, etc.)|to get a better opinion of|
（フィー）ラビィ 見直したよ
I was wrong
about you, Lavie!
ちきしょう:beast (i.e. any animal other than man)|person reborn into the animal realm, 今夜[こんや]:this evening/tonight, 飲む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||
ちきしょう 今夜は飲むぞ！
Oh, screw it! I'm gonna
throw some back tonight!
You're all invited! Got it?!
つきあえる:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, つきあえる:to poke each other/to jab each other
みんなもつきあえ いいな！
コピー:copy/photocopy
（一同）ウィー コピー
We copy!
おかえりなさい:welcome home
（タナベ）おかえりなさい
Welcome back!
ああ
Hey.
Lately, I had been thinking that you
haven't been acting like yourself,
最近[さいきん]:most recent/these days/right now, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
最近の先輩 らしくないなって
思ってたんですけど
...but you're still in there,
all right!
やっぱり:too/also|still, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, いざというとき:when it's important/when it comes to the crunch/when push comes to shove, ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly
でも やっぱり先輩ですね
いざというときには ちゃんと
When the chips were down,
you came through just fine!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 成功[せいこう]:success/hit
先輩が
あのＥＶＡを成功させたから―
We were able to shut down the mine
because you pulled off your EVA!
機雷[きらい]:(sea) mine, 止める[とめる]:to stop|to park|to prevent||, 止める[やめる]:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel
機雷を止めることが
できたんですよ
やっぱり:too/also|still, すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
やっぱり すごいです
You're amazing,
all right!
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
そうか 俺は すごいか
I am? You think I'm amazing?
（タナベ）ええ！
Yep!
タナベ
Tanabe.
はい
Yes?
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 辞める[やめる]:to resign/to retire/to quit
（ハチマキ）俺 会社 辞めるわ
I'm quitting
the company.
は？
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 解散[かいさん]:breakup/dissolution
でも デブリ課が
解散っていうだけで まだ…
But they only said that Debris Section
was disbanded. There's still...
No, it's not about that. It's just that...
いや そのことじゃなくて その…
デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 終わり[おわり]:the end
デブリ屋は もう終わりだ
I'm not a hauler anymore.
I'm done with debris.
♪～
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
♪～
Next Time
Endings are Always...